Hi, welcome back to Arja Nagarjuna.
And here we go.
We're now reached the 17th chapter
which is LAS KYI BRTAGS PA
It's a investigation
into the nature of karma
and the seeds for karma.
And we went through and we
were saying that this chapter
is unusual because we can understand it.
It doesn't even seem like Nagarjuna.
Don't worry. He's going to lose us later.
And personally,
I was wondering why he
went through sort of
the Abhidharma presentation on karma,
dividing it into intention,
and the actions of body
and speech that are intended.
And then he went through
some kind of obscure
Abhidharma ideas about
different kinds of karma
that you can see a person's intention,
or a halo, or an aura forms
around them, good or bad.
And then that's another kind of karma.
Do you guys want to, anybody
want to make a 100 dollars
and guess why he's going through obscure
Abhidharma presentations of karma?
[student speaking indistinctly]
No, that's -- Why? Why
is he working on that?
[student speaking indistinctly]
The answer is more easy than that.
- [Student] Because everyone
was an Abhidharma student.
- Yay! How much I say? A hundred dollars?
- [Student] Yes.
- Pachi, $100. Don't forget to tell Elly.
Yeah, everybody was
Abhidharma at that time
for seven hundred years.
And then he was trying to
reverse that tidal wave.
And he did, by the way, single-handedly.
He stood in front of
a whole ocean of accountants
from the Abhidharma school,
and he turned them all into hippies, yay.
So anyway.
So here he is going, okay,
and we were wondering if you remember
why he didn't just
describe the ten good deeds
and ten bad deeds,
and guess what he does next, you ready?
,DKAR PO'I LAS KYI LAM BCU PO,
,CHOS SGRUB PA YI THABS YIN TE,
,CHOS KYI 'BRAS BU 'DI GZHAN DU,
,'DOD PA'I YON TAN RNAM LNGA'O,
DKAR PO'I LAS means white
karma or good karma.
LAM BCU PO -- the 10 paths.
So the 10 good deeds,
the 10 commandments in Buddhism are called
the 10 paths of white karma.
CHOS SGRUB ... CHOS SGRUB PA YI THABS
These are a method of achieving dharma.
And then Choney Lama says,
"When Nagarjuna says dharma
here, Arya Nagarjuna,
he means a higher births
and definite good."
Definite good is called NGES LEGS,
and it means nirvana and Buddhahood.
So when Nagarjuna says
in the first line and a half
there are 10 paths of white karma and
these are a method of
achieving the Dharma,
he means a higher birth,
and nirvana, and Buddhahood.
CHOS KYI 'BRAS BU 'DI GZHAN DU
Then the line just says,
"The result of this
Dharma is this and other."
Anybody want to take a guess
of what this an other is?
You get good results in
this life and other lives.
dirstha-adirstha. Right?
Seen in this life and
seen in future lives.
'DOD PA'I YON TAN RNAM LNGA'O
And especially, you're going
to get 'DOD PA'I YON TAN,
the good stuff of the desire realm.
Nice things to eat,
nice music to listen to,
soft blankets, you know,
just think of the wonders
of your future life
when you follow these
10 good deeds, you know,
what a cushy life you're going to have.
You're going to get expensive
creams for your face.
And I don't know about you,
but I start to... I'm like,
that's weird.
It doesn't seem, it doesn't seem like
Nagarjuna to say
you're going to get a new car,
your hair is going to grow back,
you're going to get energy, you know?
And then we find out from Choney Lama,
he is criticizing. Okay, got it?
He's saying "Oh, great,
the 10 good deeds." - What? -
More money, more car, more hair.
You're going to be healthy.
And then we find out from Choney Lama,
this is Nagarjuna sort of saying,
"Look how people talk about karma.
Look how these guys talk about karma."
You look at the purposes
they want to put karma to,
and then he's criticizing them.
And what he criticizes
is deeper than you think.
It's fine to get a lot of money.
It's fine to get a nice car.
It's fine to have a good apartment.
But it's not fine to think
that there's a self existent
relationship between doing the
"10" and getting that stuff.
- Is it okay to have a
nice apartment? - Yes.
- Can I be, can I have a big bank account?
- Yeah, that's fine. You
can help more people.
- Can I have a big car?
- Yeah. You can fit more people or
go to parties at John Brady's house.
And then [laughs], okay,
but if you think there's
a self existing connection
between helping other people
or doing the Medicine Buddha mantra,
and getting all these nice things,
if you think that connection
doesn't come from you,
then something's going to
happen in the next verse.
So the next verse kind of reveals
what we're really thinking about.
By the way, I like this...
Choney Lama says he has a side
comment on that last verse.
And there's the picture
that he's using with the guy
with the airplane tickets.
And he says, "By the way,
this verse in general is a
criticism of people who are
focusing on karma to get stuff.
Not because the stuff is wrong,
but because their feeling
about the connection
between the karma and
the stuff is too solid."
They don't understand the
emptiness of that connection.
He says so that's okay.
We could also say... we could've
added another line to this
verse that said you will get
house, you'll get apartment,
you know, you'll get healthy,
and you'll get enlightened [laughs].
He said if it was me,
I would have added a line to the verse.
One more line.
So just be aware of that
guy with the airplane ticket
and a passport: that's a
passport to enlightenment.
Which is also comes from the
10 good deeds. All right.
Then the next verse
reveals Nagarjuna's opinion
about the last verse.
And here it goes.
,GAL TE BRTAG PA DER 'GYUR NA,
,NYES PA CHEN PO MANG POR 'GYUR,
If you do that kind of BRTAG PA,
what's BRTAG PA?
B-R-T-A-G
ba rata ta BRTA ga BRTAG
- [Woman] Pariksha.
- Yeah, pariksha.
If you do, if that's
the best investigation
you can do on karma,
NYES PA CHEN PO MANG PO
you're going to get into
a big pile of problems,
many big piles of problems [laughs].
So Nagarjuna is like,
the other guy can just see him, he's like,
well, I was just saying you
should do the 10 good deeds
because you can get
lots of money and stuff.
He says, God, think
like, you do the pariksha
like that, big trouble, big, big,
so many problems is
going to come from that.
Doing your Medicine Buddha mantra is
because you think you're going to be
healthy later, just for that,
and to think there's
a connection like that
between the mantra and the good health,
NYES PA CHEN PO MANG POR 'GYUR,
you're going to get into
a lot of problems later.
Like what?
,DE LTA BAS NA BRTAG PA DE,
,'DIR NI 'THAD PA MA YIN NO,
Then Nagarjuna goes further.
He says, your kind of pariksha
is an anti-pariksha.
Okay?
Your investigation is
"estupido" investigation.
[students laughing]
Okay, got it?
- That's an idiot's investigation.
- What?
- You're going to use karma
just to get some money
or just to cure your hair or something.
It's just, by the way,
not wrong to get money,
not wrong to get hair,
just wrong to think there's
an automatic connection.
It's how you think about the mantra.
It's not the mantra.
All right.
And I have two kids here.
These are twins.
And you know, when you see them,
you assume it's a picture of two twins,
but that's an assumption.
They may not be twins at all.
They may just be from,
they may just look similar.
Yeah, you can do the mantra
and something might happen.
But is there a connection between the two?
Is it really what you think you see?
All right.
And that takes us to the next verse.
,SANGS RGYAS RNAMS DANG RANG RGYAL DANG,
,NYAN THOS RNAMS KYIS GANG GSUNGS PA'I,
,BRTAG PA GANG ZHIG 'DIR 'THAD PA,
,DE NI RAB TU BRJOD PAR BYA,
By the way,
there is an investigation into karma
that you could've done
which would've been a
better investigation,
not "estupedo".
You could've had a smart investigation.
- Which one is that?
- Well, it was described by the Buddha
and by the self-made buddhas
and by the great listeners,
these are arhats,
people who reached nirvana.
If you're going to do an
investigation into karma,
I suggest you follow their investigation
and not your investigation [laughs].
Okay?
Not think there's a
self existing connection
between Medicine Buddha
mantra and those, you know,
money and good health.
- I suggest you shift your investigation.
- To what?
- To the one that the Buddha described.
All right.
- Well, what's that?
DE NI RAB TU BRJOD PAR BYA
I'm going to tell you.
I'm going to tell you so perfectly.
RAB TU means I'm going to
set you straight, 100%.
Then he goes off on a very deep
subject and difficult subject.
So finally,
Nagarjuna took off the gloves,
and he's going to show you his real style.
So here he goes.
Fasten your seatbelts.
Here we go. Okay.
,DPANG RGYA JI LTAR DE BZHIN CHUD,
,MI ZA
,MI ZA LAS NI BU LON BZHIN,
And there's a bunch of
problems in the carvings,
but I figured it out.
So DPANG RGYA means a contract.
And it's often used for loans.
When you borrow money 2000 years ago,
you have to sign a DPANG RGYA.
Or when you get married, you
have to sign a DPANG RGYA.
So it could be a marriage contract
and it could be a loan agreement.
He says DPANG RGYA DE BZHIN
DPANG RGYA JI LTAR DE BZHIN CHUD
And you have to read across the lines.
You have to say CHUD MI ZA.
And you guys know CHUD MI ZA,
I taught to you in the LAM RIM
over, and over, and over again.
Four laws of karma.
BYAS PA CHUD MI ZA BA
The fourth of the laws of karma.
If you do do something,
you will get a result.
BYAS PA CHUD MI ZA BA
Literally, BYAS PA means
if you do something,
CHUD MI ZA BA means
it's not just kind of fade away over time.
You can't hope that you
can lie to your mom,
and then the karma is just going
to wear out sooner or later
before 20 people lie back to you.
Like you can't,
you shouldn't hope that
you can do something wrong,
keep it quiet, don't tell anybody,
and after time everyone's going to forget,
because that's not how karma works.
Everything's recorded
and everything expands.
So, you know, he says that principle,
CHUD MI ZA BA, don't forget that word
because we're going to
have to come back to it
over and over again,
in this part. CHUD MI ZA BA means
in Tibetan, karma's not
just going to fade away
if you wait long enough.
In fact, the opposite.
So don't think CHUD MI ZA BA.
Now, he says that, in Abhidharma,
you can take a general proof
and in the Abhidharma school
it becomes a tool.
The fact that CHUD MI ZA BA,
the fact that karma doesn't just fade away
in Abhidharma system is a separate thing.
It's a real thing, like a cup or a table.
Hey, did you bring your cup?
- Yeah. Did you put it on the table?
- Yeah. - How's your CHUD MI ZA BA doing?
- What?
- How's the fact that your
karma is not going to fade away?
How's that feel this morning?
And in fact, in the Abhidharma system,
every time you do anything,
you also do a CHUD MI ZA BA.
You give money, you do a CHUD MI ZA BA.
Got it?
You do a nice thing for somebody,
you pick up another CHUD MI ZA BA.
You put it... here's
another CHUD MI ZA BA,
means that good deed is
not going to just go away.
So good could be for
good deeds or bad deeds.
And they do that in Abhidharma.
They have the idea like THOB PA.
When you achieve nirvana, what
connects you to the nirvana?
Then in fact, there's
a problem in Abhidharma
because you're not there anymore.
Then you got to get an achievement.
And it's an entity.
It's like a cup.
- Do you have an achievement?
Did you reach nirvana yesterday? - Yes.
- Did they give you an achievement? - No.
- Oh my God, that you're going
to, it's going to fall off.
Get an achievement [laughs].
So it's called a THOB PA.
So now we're going to go
off on a subject called...
What do you want to call that in English?
CHUD MI ZA BA, it don't go away?
Did you get "a don't go away"?
Did you pick up "a don't go away"
when you donated the money to ALL?
Were you careful to get "a don't go away"
from Pau when you made
the donation to the club?
Club de oro?
Did she also give you "a don't go away"?
Did you get a don't, did you
pick up "a don't go away"?
Okay. Got it?
It's a contract, in a way.
- We guarantee that you're
going to have prosperity.
- Why?
- You just donated money to
the most important project
in the universe.
So we give you a written guarantee,
that's called a DPANG RGYA or
CHUD MI ZA BA'I DPANG RGYA.
That's a don't go away contract.
Okay. Got it?
Because we're going to spend
now like a couple of hours
on don't go away contracts.
Phew.
BU LON BZHIN means it's
like when you take a loan.
BU LON BZHIN means it's similar
to when you take a loan.
They give you a contract and you sign it.
When you take the money,
you get the contract,
the don't go away contract.
That don't go away means you
don't go away without paying back.
All right.
So you can have a don't go away
with good things and with bad things.
All right, here we go.
We're going to dig deeper into?
- [Students] Don't go aways.
- Don't go aways.
It's a noun, right? All right.
And that's going to be pretty
much the rest of the chapter.
Now, Nagarjuna is going to
repeat what the last 700 years
of guys said about don't go aways.
Don't go aways
- What's the don't go away look like?
- Well, I'll tell you.
,DE NI KHAMS LAS RNAM PA BZHI,
According to KHAMS meaning
dhatu, meaning realm.
Those can be divided into three.
You've got don't go aways
in the desire realm,
you've got don't go
aways in the form realm,
you've got don't go aways
in the formless realm,
but he says four. Why?
In the Abhidharma system,
you can have something outside the realms.
And that's pure things,
ZAG BCAS, "vimala" things,
like nirvana or Buddhahood.
He says you can get a don't go away
that's not in sansara.
It's outside the sansara.
So let's call it four,
three for the sansaric realms
and one that's outside of sansara.
Four don't go aways.
Whose idea?
Abhidharma. Abhidharma.
Choney Lama said BYE
BRAG SMRA BA 'GA' ZHIG
meaning some Detailists,
some Abhidharma guys.
All right, so first you can
divide it into four types
depending on where that
don't go away is residing.
What's next?
,DE YANG RANG BZHIN LUNG MA BSTAN,
What's LUNG MA BSTAN? You guys know this.
DGE BA, it's not DGE BA.
It's not MI DGE BA.
- [Student] Neutral.
- Yeah, karmically neutral.
And that's a little tricky.
A lot of these instruments
which keeps spiritual stuff on you
are karmically neutral themselves.
So a don't go away,
a contract isn't good or bad.
I mean there can be bad
stuff in the contract,
or there can be good
but the papers like, you
know, the instrument,
the vehicle for the contract,
which is a don't go away, is neutral.
He's like paper.
Then you can write
something nasty on the paper
or you can write something
nice on the paper,
but the don't go away is neutral.
And then it could be a bad
one. It could be a good one.
All right. Next verse.
,SPONG BAS SPANG BA MA YIN TE,
,BSGOM PAS SPANG BA NYID KYANG YIN,
There's a mistake in the carving.
Let me fix that one.
Okay.
SPONG BAS SPANG BA MA
YIN TE, very important.
It is not eliminated by MTHONG LAM.
Yeah.
You can see emptiness directly,
and it doesn't do anything
to your don't go aways.
Okay.
Delicate question.
But by the way, Nagarjuna
is trying to impress on us.
What's a don't go away? What
makes karma stick to you?
What makes karma stick to you?
Well, it's don't go aways.
What's a don't go away like?
Well, it's karmacally neutral.
It could be in different realms
and unfortunately you don't
drop the don't go aways
when you see emptiness directly.
But maybe you get rid of the bad karma,
but keep the don't go away?
Okay. Question.
We're not sure yet.
Okay.
And BSGOM PAS SPANG BA NYID KYANG YIN,
it is eliminated by the
path of habituation.
$100, tell me why it should be.
$100.
Don't forget what school we're in.
And what if I say a don't go away
can be eliminated at the end of
the path of habituation.
- Why? What happens there?
Lower school, lower school.
- [Woman] End of suffering.
- I want more precision.
For a $100 I need at least two words.
[student speaking indistinctly]
Lower school, lower school.
Okay. I'm cutting it to $50.
BEM RIG RGYUN CHAD PA
Cut the flow of BEM PO
and RIG PA. Lower nirvana.
For $12 [laughs].
Ah, forget the bet, BEM PO
means your material body.
And RIG PA means your mind.
RGYUN CHAD PA means, in the
lower school, you blink out.
[fingers snapping]
You just blink out.
Then you don't suffer anymore. Yay!
Then the debate by the higher schools
is not too complicated.
- What's nirvana according to you?
[hands slapping]
- You blink out. - What?
- Your body blinks out, your
mind blinks out? - Right.
- What do we call you then?
- Arhat. - Where's Arhat?
[laughing]
- [Woman] Nowhere.
- [laughs] It's a very funny,
that's an ancient debate.
[hands clapping]
- Where's the Arhat [laughs]?
All right.
So probably your don't go aways
are going to finish if your...
[student speaking indistinctly]
body and mind finish [laughs].
All right
,DE PHYIR CHUD MI ZA BA YIS,
,LAS KYI 'BRAS BU SKYED PAR 'GYUR,
Don't forget, we were having
this trouble of saying
if the karmic seed changes, right?
Sorry, if it doesn't change,
it can't give a result.
And if it does change, moment by moment,
[fingers snapping]
it disappears in one 65th of a second.
So how can it transmit your...
how can there be a CHUD MI ZA BA?
How can there be a, what do we call it?
[student speaking indistinctly]
No, what's the word we use?
How can the don't go away flow over time
if it's instant, coming in and out
of existence, moment by moment?
Then he says here
DE PHYIR CHUD MI ZA BA YIS
it's not the karmic seed that
creates the karmic result.
It's the don't go away.
[students laughing]
It's the seed comes and go,
but the don't go away stay.
Then when the seed disappears,
the don't go away stays with you.
And then the don't go away
gives you the money later.
After you give a donation, got it?
The don't go away can stay.
Got it? [laughs]
Okay. This is okay.
I can see you're impressed
with this idea [laughs].
,GAL TE SPONG BAS SPANG BA DANG,
,LAS 'PHO BA YIS 'JIG 'GYUR NA,
If the don't go aways could disappear,
just because you reached a
higher path in the five paths,
or just because something's
happened to your karma in general,
then DE LA LAS 'JIG LA SOGS PA'I
Then LAS BYAS PA CHUD ZA BA.
Say LAS BYAS PA CHUD ZA
BA. [students repeat]
Then you could hurt somebody
and never get a result
which breaks every law of karma and
everything the Buddha ever said.
If the don't go away could be eliminated
even by great spiritual attainments,
then you're saying you could do
a bad deed and get no result.
Not possible. Okay?
So the don't go away has to stay [laughs].
Maybe it doesn't create
anything, I don't know.
,SKYON RNAMS SU NI THAL BAR 'GYUR,
look at all the problems you're causing.
Then he says SOGS, he
says other problems too.
And then Choney Lama says,
"Are you curious about what
the other problem was?"
And we're like, "Yeah, we
were really wondering."
And he says LAS MA BYAS
BA DANG MA PHRAD PA
Problem number three, law
number three of karma.
Yeah, if you don't do it, you're
not going to get a problem.
If you don't steal money,
you're never going to lose money.
Karmic law number three:
if you don't do it,
you don't get a result.
Karmic law number four,
if you do do it, it's not
going to just fade away.
Okay. Got it?
So the CHUD MI ZA BA
principle of... what was it?
Don't go away.
The don't go away is so useful
because we can still keep
the last two laws of karma.
Okay.
All right, here we go.
By the way, I have a Titanic sinking here.
Are you ready, Pachi?
I worked so hard.
You know,
there's no pictures of
the Titanic sinking?
[students laughing]
So I got this one for you guys [laughs].
And okay, by the way,
if the Titanic, if you had a credit card,
when you got on the Titanic
and you used it a lot
on the Titanic, and then it sank,
how's your DPANG RGYA?
How's your credit card bill?
What's it going to look like?
- [Student] Zero.
- Zero! Okay, got it?
Your don't go aways sank with the Titanic.
That represents nirvana:
the discontinuation of your body and mind.
That's the sinking of the Titanic.
It also takes your credit card bills.
Nobody on the Titanic got
charged for the food and drink,
I wonder, probably not, right?
The company probably failed the next day.
So anyway, I thought it was a cute example
of discontinuation of body and mind.
And then all those DPANG RGYAs,
all those credit card agreements
went down with the ship.
Then maybe nirvana is defined by finally
you escaped your credit
card bills [laughs].
Why? There's no body or mind
left to pay them. Got it?
Okay.
Isn't it cute photo? Yes.
I thought we should take
a vacation to the Sanskrit
for don't go away.
What's the Sanskrit for a don't go away?
And here you go.
Avipraṇāśa (avipranasha), avipranasha.
It's probably an Israeli, right, avi?
Hey, Avi, pranasha.
So it's four parts a-vi-pra-nasha.
So please repeat, a-vi-pra-nasha.
Sorry, naasha.
A-vi-pra-naasha.
Okay, so a- means? Christina?
- [Christina] Not.
- Not. Vi- means very much.
Pra- means super, and the root √naś
means to be lost or to fade away.
Got it?
Very much completely didn't fade away.
A-vi-pra-naasha. Got it?
So you can use the Sanskrit.
Hey, you got any don't go aways?
Sorry. You got any avipranashas?
Yeah, I got some avipranashas.
I hope I can keep the avipranashas
of my donation to the Gold Club.
And I hope I can lose the avipranaashas
when I reach nirvana of
all my credit cards debts.
All right.
So learn the word.
Generally, √naś as a root in Sanskrit
means to be destroyed or to be lost.
It's probably connected
to "not". All right.
Next verse.
By the way it's a long chapter. I'm sorry.
But I know you guys are fascinated.
Okay. Now the other guy says,
"Well, if you can lose your avipranashas,"
it sounds like a Jewish pastry.
[students laughing]
Right? I don't know.
Where's that nice bakery,
is it still there?
On...?
- [Woman] Oh, on second ave?
- Yeah. No?
- [Woman] You know, that one
was in and out of business
all the time.
- No, but it was there
for like a hundred years.
- [Woman] Yeah, hopefully
it opens back up.
- Okay. Anyway, you can pick
up some avipranashas there.
Anyway, the guy says, "Okay,
"I understand that if the Titanic sinks,
"all the credit card bills go,
but what about life to life?
"Do you lose your avipranaashas
when you skip to a new life,
"when you cross the border,
NYING MTSAMS SBYOR BA,
"into a new rebirth, do the
avipranashas come with you?"
Do the can't go aways
come with you or not?
What do you guess, by the way?
- [Student] Yes.
- They do go away?
- [Students] No.
- They probably don't go away.
Otherwise, there would be
no karma in the next life.
Okay. Here's the real answer.
,KHAMS MTSUNGS LAS NI CHA MTSUNGS DANG,
If you go from the same
rebirth to the same rebirth,
if you go from human to human,
you keep your avipranashas.
Or if you go from desire
realm to desire realm,
you keep your avipranashas.
,CHA MI MTSUNGS PA THAMS CAD KYI,
There might be some not keeping
your avipranashas when you
change to a different realm
because those devas
are not going to have the obvious
suffering that you should
have had if you were born
in the human realm, right?
If you had gone from the human
realm to the human realm,
you'd be having some gross
sufferings that devas don't have.
So if you go from human to deva,
something must have happened to some
of your avipranashas for trouble
because they don't have trouble. Got it?
All right.
Now I mean, when you go from a human birth
to a deva birth, in that birth
you don't have the gross pain
that you have in this realm.
Nobody breaks their arm in the deva realm.
It doesn't happen.
So maybe something happens
to your avipranashas,
if you go to a different realm
from a human realm. All right.
,CHA MI MTSUNGS PA THAMS CAD KYI,
,DE NI NYING MTSAMS SBYOR BA'I TSE,
,GCIG PO KHO NA SKYE BAR 'GYUR,
But, okay, ready?
I'm sorry.
Your karma might not go with you,
but your avipranasha will go with you.
How's that?
Your karma may not go with you,
but your, what did we call it...
your don't go away will
go with you. How's that?
This is all Abhidharma. Okay. I'm sorry.
By the way, the only reason why
Nagarjuna would give a lot
of wild Abhidharma ideas
as if he's going to
destroy them at some point.
[everyone laughing]
I'm just, I'm just telling you.
All right, next verse.
Sorry, next verse.
,MTHONG BA'I CHOS LA RNAM GNYIS PO,
Now MTHONG BA'I CHOS can mean
something you saw at the path of seeing,
but it can also mean dirsta-adirsta,
seen in this life or
seen in the future life.
And that's what it means here.
So as far as, are you going to see it,
as far as dirsta-adirsta
when you do any kind
of...well, how should we say?
anytime you commit a karma in this life,
your won't go away is dirsta in this life.
You pick it up in this life.
Whatever karma you committed in this life,
you pick up a don't go
away for that in this life.
Dirsta, it's seen in this life.
RNAM GNYIS PO
And that could apply
to ZAG BCAS or ZAG MED
in the Abhidharma system.
Good karmas... impure
karmas or pure karmas
which is a long subject.
,KUN GYI [THAMS CAD] LAS DANG LAS KYI DE,
Also, both types of chetana
and chetayitva,
chetana and chetayitva.
We studied it a long time ago, yesterday.
[student laughing]
Chetana comes from √cit.
[student speaking indistinctly]
Chetana.
Yeah. Yeah.
Intention and intended.
So that division, he says,
whether you commit a karma mentally,
or whether you commit
a karma because of what
you were thinking, both of them,
you still pick up a don't go away.
Whether it's mental karma,
which is thinking karma,
which is intention, or it's
the action of body or speech,
which was intended by that,
you still pick up a don't go away.
This is all details of don't go aways.
Avipranasha.
,THA DAD PAR NI SKYE 'GYUR ZHING,
This is cool.
You get a separate don't go away
every time you make a karma.
So you're basically collecting
don't go aways your whole life.
Your whole life your pockets
filling up with don't go aways.
Every tiny thing you do,
you get a new don't go away.
It's discreet.
It says here THA DAD, THA DAD PAR SKYE,
it arises discreetly,
,RNAM PAR SMIN KYANG GNAS PA YIN,
This is really controversial.
After the karma ripens, the
don't go away stays with you.
Well, what's it do [laughs]?
Don't ask me.
He doesn't say, but
according to Abhidharma,
the don't go away stays with you,
even if the karma is
destroyed or it ripens,
and it finishes.
Even if the seed finishes,
the don't go away stays with you somehow.
So we must be collecting
zillions of don't go aways.
What do they do if they don't hold
the karma anymore, I don't know.
It's kind of like an empty pocket
after you spend all your money.
I guess you could still have the pocket.
All right.
Now the Abhidharma guy says, "Nagarjuna,
you forgot to tell them how to get rid of
your don't go aways."
And Nagarjuna is like "ah,
yeah, let's talk about"
So here's how to get rid
of your don't go aways,
extra don't go aways.
All right.
,DE NI 'BRAS BU 'PHO BA DANG,
,SHI BAR GYUR NA 'GAG PAR 'GYUR,
The second part here is easy.
If you're SHI BA,
you lose your don't go aways.
- [Student] If you die.
- Yeah, if die, you lose
some don't go aways.
Doesn't seem to make sense
because you should be able to
carry it into your next life.
'BRAS BU 'PHO BA means serious,
heavy graduating karmic result.
This refers to a stream enterer,
once returner, non-returner, and arhat.
These are called the four fruits.
When the fruit is big, heavy good karma,
heavy spiritual realizations, "yeah,
it could cancel your don't go aways."
And I can, I don't know,
but I'm imagining SBYOR LAM BZOD,
the mastery level of SBYOR LAM.
You can't go to a lower realm anymore,
so they must've destroyed
your don't go aways.
It must have damaged some
of your don't go aways.
But then he just said
that can only be lost when you
become an arhat, I don't know.
Okay.
,DE YI RNAM DBYE ZAG MED DANG,
,ZAG DANG BCAS PAR SHES PAR BYA,
You could have enlightened don't go aways
and you can have sansaric don't go aways.
Everyone in the room is going to sleep.
Let's see if we can go on [Laughs].
I like this picture, okay, Pachi?
I built my Lama's house.
It took me... Oh wait, there's
one more picture of him.
Yeah. I built my Lama's house.
I paid for it and I built it
and no one came to help me.
I mean, one guy helped me
for a day or something.
So I was up on these high...,
it's two stories high, I
was up in the third story
on the ladder and I'll never forget it.
It was winter, dead of winter.
I'm up on the ladder,
painting the house like this.
And these people would come,
Mongolian old men and
they'd say "Hey, Mike."
I'm like what?
He said, "I got to go to the store."
I'm like, "I'm painting the house
that no one's helping me paint."
And he said, "But I'm going
to store, I need a ride.
I was the SPYI PA'I RTA,
I was the public horse of the
whole community, so anyway.
So why am I talking about that?
If you get high enough, you
leave the toolbox at the bottom.
If you're working on the third story,
you always forget some tool.
And then you have to climb down
this very dangerous ladder,
two stories, get the
screwdriver and go back up.
And then you forgot the paint, you know.
And you're by yourself.
Anyway, what I'm saying
is if you get high enough,
you can leave some of your
don't go aways behind.
I don't know why that image, anyway.
All right.
Let's go to the next verse.
So we start saying, we start thinking,
well, then this whole don't go away thing
is starting to sound a
little uncomfortable.
This feels like really a lower idea
that once you commit a
karma, it can't just go away.
It starts to feel uncomfortable, right?
This whole idea of a don't go away,
you know, it sounds weird.
Then suddenly Nagarjuna shifts gears.
He says, following verse,
,STONG PA NYID DANG TSAD MED DANG,
,'KHOR BA DANG NI RTAG PA MIN,
,LAS RNAMS CHUD MI ZA BA'I CHOS,
,SANGS RGYAS KYIS NI BSTAN PA YIN,
Who taught don't go aways?
- [Student] The Buddha.
- The Buddha.
So Nagarjuna says, "Hey,
don't think don't go aways
are stupid idea, there's
a real don't go away."
As he seems to shift gears
here, he's like look,
I know you guys now, you don't have
much respect for don't go aways,
but there is a real don't go away.
Let me tell you about
the real don't go away.
And then he starts to describe it.
STONG PA NYID
Don't think that just
because something is empty,
it's going to destroy the don't go away.
Don't go aways do exist.
And they are empty.
But that doesn't mean
they don't keep your seed.
Okay?
Don't think that don't go aways
can't hold your karma
with you for lifetimes
just because they are empty.
That's a misunderstanding empty.
When I say a don't go away is empty,
I don't mean it doesn't work
because you guys keeps thinking
that every time I say empty,
you guys think it doesn't matter anymore.
But when I say empty, I mean
it does matter [laughs].
Don't go aways are empty.
Therefore you better learn
about them and respect them
because it means they work.
It doesn't mean they don't work.
So that's the first thing
Nagarjuna has to say.
STONG PA NYID CHAD PA
CHAD PA means...
when we say BEM RIG RGYUN CHAD PA,
when you cut off the flow
of something... anyway,
let's say cut off.
[student speaking indistinctly]
- Terminate? Truncate.
It should be CHAD PA, STONG
PA NYID DANG CHAD PA DANG.
Oh, that's... hm-hm.
Yeah, that's certainly a mistake.
By the way, I mixed the Tengyur
version and the Choney Lama's versions,
so I could detect problems.
I have the Choney Lama's version,
you have the Tengyur version.
And the reason I did that, so
I could detect any problems.
So anyway,
STONG PA NYID DANG CHAD PA DANG
So don't think that's because it's empty
your don't go away it's
just going to disappear.
CHAD PA -- truncate.
We had the two extremes,
thinking things are unchanging
and thinking things just stop.
Third thing.
'KHOR BA
"You better figure out
this don't go away thing,"
says Nagarjuna, "first of all,
because the Buddha said it and secondly,
because it is the king of
sansara. It runs sansara.
Don't go aways run sansara.
They are the bus drivers for sansara.
The don't go aways in your karmic pocket
are the bus driver of your sansara.
So you goddamn better figur it out
because they keep your karmas with you.
So you better figure it out.
So he says this is not BS.
This is real.
The Buddha talked about it.
We have to figure it out
because they are running your suffering.
Last thing.
RTAG PA MIN
Don't think they are unchanging.
That's not correct.
Don't think that a karma stored over
time would have to be unchanging.
That's also a misperception.
The Buddha did say karma
can be stored over time
and come back to you,
that doesn't mean that
karma is unchanging.
It just means it's replicating
or something like that.
So what he's saying is
I've made a lot of fun
of the Abhidharma guys in
a bunch of verses here,
but actually they're pretty cool.
This idea that you could,
that karma don't go away
that's for real, that's for real.
He says,
"I just brought it up because
you guys think if it's empty,
"a don't go away can't work.
"But I want to tell you if it's empty,
"that's the proof that it can
work and karma will stay with you,
"so you better watch your karma.
"This don't go away stuff is real."
- Why? - Buddha said so.
That's Nagarjuna.
It seems like a long class,
but it's okay, right?
All right, here we go.
,GANG PHYIR LAS NI SKYE BA MED,
,'DI LTAR RANG BZHIN MED DE'I PHYIR,
,GANG PHYIR DE NI MA SKYES PA,
,DE PHYIR CHUD ZAR MI 'GYUR RO,
Then Nagarjuna goes into why
a don't go away should work.
Nagarjuna goes into why a
don't go away should work.
And he says LAS NI SKYE BA MED,
don't go aways work because
you cannot do karma.
Don't go aways work because
Meaning which exists from its own side.
So he's kicking, you know. Now he's
like, yay, finally, I confused you.
[everyone laughing]
I'll say it again.
Don't go aways work because
karma... you cannot do karma.
you cannot do karma.
'DI LTAR RANG BZHIN MED DE'I PHYIR
- Why?
- Because karma doesn't
have any nature of its own.
It's coming from your seed.
GANG PHYIR DE NI MA SKYES PA
And because you cannot do karma,
it's going to stay with
you without going away.
Because you cannot do karma,
it's going to stay with you
and cannot just go away.
Because you cannot do karma,
you do get don't go aways.
Got it?
Because you cannot do karma,
you do get those don't go aways.
- [Christina] And that sounds like karma
don't go aways are the same thing.`
- Uh. Don't go aways
keep karma on Christina,
whoever Christina is.
- [Christina] Like a glue?
- Yeah, it's like a glue.
This is a very Abhidharma idea.
By the way, if you want to get,
if you really want to ask questions,
what keeps the glue on you?
- [Christina] Right.
- Then they, Abhidharma
says, THOB PA'I THOB PA.
You got to have a glue for the glue.
Then they say, then the other guy says,
do you have THOB PA'I THOB PA'I THOB PA,
do you have glue for
the glue for the glue?
And they say, "Nope, it ends
at the glue for the glue."
[everone laughing]
Okay.
So don't worry.
You don't need glue for your glue.
You don't need glues for your glue glue,
but you do need glue for your glue.
All right.
I like this next picture.
It's called The Rules.
Why stuff works?
And the rules.
I like to say the rules hold
true because they don't exist.
You got to follow the rules of karma
because they don't exist.
Meaning even the laws of
karma are coming from you.
Well, then Geshe-la they
should be adjustable.
If the laws of karma are coming from me,
then I should be able to do a good deed
and get a bad result,
you know, under weird circumstances.
If it's coming from me,
then I should be able to
mess with the laws of karma.
And that's a fallacy.
The fact that something's coming from you
doesn't mean you can change it.
That there's not patterns.
That there's not inevitable patterns.
The fact that something's
coming from you is not a proof
that there are not
inevitable patterns in life.
And that if you hurt someone,
you're going to get hurt.
- Are you creating that law? - Yes.
- Can you change that law? - No.
- Well, if it's coming
from you, I can change it.
MA KHYAB - not necessarily.
Okay?
[hands clapping]
We'll talk about it.
It's a tough class.
Listen to it a bunch of times.
We're not done with our
examination of karma.
We've got one more class to go.
See you, next one.